imagine your editing is so good that
your viewers can't resist watching until
the end I want that for you so I've
boiled down my years of editing
experience into a four pillar formula by
the way you'll have to take notes today
because we are going way deeper than
basic things like cutting out Dead Space
editing is so much more than that and
let's be real your video deserves so
much more than
that a great editing style may get you
perfect watch time and millions of views
but it may also leave you with terrible
view counts and Broken Dreams to figure
out why let's start with
this it's just this guy Sam in his car
talking and then working out the video
lasts 26 minutes but has just 17 cuts
and no other form of editing how many
views how many subscribers do you expect
him to
have so this means that editing is
optional right wait slow down that's not
what's going on here Sam did edit he cut
out all the boring parts that the viewer
didn't come to see but he left it at
that because his viewers aren't looking
for a super stimulating experience they
just want to feel like they're spending
time with someone a bunch of Quick Cuts
and flashy animations would ruin that
authentic experience that the viewer
wanted and guess what A disruption of
what the viewer came to the video for is
the best way to make them stop watching
and while Sam edits with an average of
90 seconds between cuts Mr Beast does
quite the opposite so if both editing
Styles work what should you do start
with considering what experience your
viewers want Sam's editing tells us that
millions of people come to YouTube to
feel like they're hanging out with
someone Mr BEAST's rapid fire style
shows that a ton of people go on YouTube
for entertainment all your editing
choices contribute to that experience
for example cutting out all your pauses
so that you're speaking constantly is is
easily the most important thing for
entertainment but it takes away from
authenticity an effective editing style
takes all these choices into account so
as I reveal the reasoning behind my
editing for my first three uploads take
notes on what you should add to your own
videos based on what suits your audience
the best this video is not a bunch of
tutorials it's a handbook to addictive
editing think of it as a foundational
starting point to know what tutorials
you should even watch in the first place
I want you to look at this there's a
problem
here this is the timeline of a typically
edited YouTube video a couple cuts have
removed the unnecessary bits there was a
tangent here that wasn't really relevant
to the video's greater purpose these
Cuts removed pauses and these removed
bad takes but in its current form this
video is doomed to fall short of its
potential the reason is this video isn't
using its visuals to maximize attention
think about this when you see a change
in your vision like something moving
abruptly it gets your attention the same
is true for watching a video and here
there's only three different things to
look at in the span of a minute kind of
boring but if the video were to switch
between a roll b roll and other types of
footage every few seconds it would keep
attention much better however there is a
drawback to changing what's on screen
too much try to notice it as we go over
how different types of footage should be
used to maximize engagement a roll this
is when you can both see and hear the
subject at the same time it feels
personal and holds attention really well
if you're speaking with confidence use
it for short periods of time when you're
saying something important b-roll this
is extra footage recorded separately
from the audio it creates a visual
depiction of your words letting the
viewer see what you're talking about
instead of just having to look at your
face this lets you get things across
much more clearly and faster too it's
more interesting than a-roll so use it
as much as possible some variants of
b-roll are stock footage which is just a
lazy version and Motion Graphics these
improve explanation times a ton look at
how quickly a complicated thing was
explained in this dude perfect video did
you find something nope I found a
suspicious looking math problem over by
the pool table and it appears that I
need to use the pool balls and the
numbers on them to form some kind of
solution you really need to understand
how crucial that editing Choice was that
was an essential but boring moment in
the video story any attempt to use a
roll or a normal b roll in this moment
would either be too slow slow or
terribly confusing both of which would
lose viewers but an animation explained
it crystal clear and fast that's the
sort of editing choice you need to make
to create an addictive video if you've
been following my channel then you've
probably noticed I've only uploaded
three videos and with that I've gotten
over 300,000 views and like 13,000
subscribers what makes it crazier is
that I haven't promoted these videos
anywhere I just uploaded them on YouTube
and they did great completely by
themselves because of all the YouTube
knowledge I've gotten over the years I
got a channel last year that I got to
like 60,000 subscribers and over 24
million views so naturally I've been
getting a ton of comments and emails of
people asking me to help them out so I
want to let you know that I'm releasing
my calendar below but it's for serious
creators only if that sounds interesting
to you then you can book a call below to
learn how to grow your YouTube channel
and by the way the spots are extremely
Limited at the moment so don't miss out
now you probably remember from earlier
there's a drawback to cutting between
different clips a ton all of this visual
variety can quickly become visual mush
if you're doing it wrong let's say you
want to be engaging so you're trying to
cut between different clips literally as
much as possible you risk making things
confusing which hurts engagement to
avoid that don't minimize shot duration
just for the sake of minimizing shot
duration it's okay to leave the same
clip on screen for for 10 seconds if
it's interesting for 10 seconds and
often times adding some engagement spice
to your video doesn't even require
cutting to another clip instead use some
of these tricks to make things way more
immersive first give some movement to
any boring still Clips you have make
either the scale or position slowly
change or even better make things Fancy
by changing their perspective you can
also do more abrupt scale changes to
draw attention to certain things for
example when I say something important
and an a-roll segment I'll zoom in close
to my face to subtly communicate to the
viewer that they should listen up you
might also make wiggle key frames that's
when you see images or text or maybe the
whole video shaking around you never see
me doing this because I don't like the
way it looks but if you want to do it
then go
ahead next throw on a bunch of visuals
on top of your
footage many people make the mistake of
adding captions just to jack up the
visual variety but don't forget that
drawback that we talked about using
captions to fill in Dead Space can
quickly become obnoxious and ruin a
great opportunity to use a more engaging
visual so I only use captions when I
want the viewer to understand and pay
closer attention to certain words but if
there's really nothing else to put on
screen captions are often still better
than nothing also keep them the three
words or less at a time because it makes
them easier to read now let's say you're
showing an image to the viewer if you
plainly show the whole thing like this
it's boring and more importantly it's
confusing to make things crystal clear
and create some visual variety guide the
viewer's attention to the focus point of
the image here are six ways that I do
that which go beyond just scaling and
positioning take notes cuz this is what
gives you professional looking timelines
like
these animate the most important piece
of text or area of the image being
highlighted darken or blur the area that
surrounds the focus point of the
image shift the Hue of the image to make
it red and it gives the image a negative
connotation you can also shift it to
yellow or green to make it seem positive
circles arrows and underlines also work
oh and one extra make the subject glow
another immersion hack is to just make
the video look good this could be color
grading adding a v yet or some subtle
particle animations on the topic of
making things look good let's bring our
Focus to make things feel good this next
pillar literally makes your video a
digital morphine
stream so we've talked about visual
variety but now let's talk about visual
continuity if you manage to create a
seamless feed of visuals then there's no
rough edges no areas for distraction to
build up there's no point where the
viewer loses immersion the goal for this
pillar is to make every moment blend
into the next seamlessly the editing
should be invisible
The Experience
mesmerizing anytime a graphic comes on
screen it can't just magically appear
there that doesn't make sense it needs
to somehow move into the frame check the
description for my free presets now you
don't have to animate things you can
also let something magically appear on
screen but then explain how it got there
using a sound effect I like to use the
shutter sound effect but a pop sound or
something like that also works now this
is super important look I just made a
cut but I messed up the most crucial
rule of doing a cut in the last frame of
this first clip the viewer is looking
right here in my eyes then a tiny
fraction of a second later in the first
frame of the second clip the viewer is
now expected to look here that's a
little jarring and it breaks some of the
immersion that your editing should be
providing imagine if every cut the
viewer had to keep changing Focus from
one side of the screen all the way to
the other this right here is a pretty
unimmersive viewing experience another
way to make cut seamless is using a full
screen transition there's plenty of free
packs out there but if you like my
subtle style of them then I got
something for you in the description and
don't be afraid to break visual
continuity every now and then cuz
remember it jolts the viewer it'll get
their attention look at this timeline
we've been talking about all these ways
to make the video visually addicting to
watch but we've been leaving out the
other half of the video there is a whole
another sense for your viewer to
experience the video in pillar four
immersive audio sound design makes the
viewer experience every cut transition
animation and piece of footage through a
second sense it's literally double the
stimulation and it can be used to
influence the mood that the viewer has
which is an engagement superpower that
we'll talk about more once we get to
your music choice but for now the first
step of sound design is to gather a
bunch of sounds to work with I already
got that for you start with that free
sound design back of copyright free
sounds that I made for you in the
description if you need more check out
freesound.org or get epidemic sound next
go through your video and basically just
add sound effects wherever it makes
sense when something moves you should
add a whoosh sound and when something's
highlighted a highlight sound now comes
the engaging part these next three types
of sound effects literally hijack your
viewers emotions and suck them into the
video first are risers they build
tension and anticipation because they
communicate to the audience that
something really important is about to
happen but only use them if something
important is actually going to happen or
else they will lose their reputation and
won't be effective next are hits these
release tension and emphasize moments
making them feel important you can use
these on their own or place a riser
before them it depends on the situation
and again don't overdo them finally
drones these create a feeling of mystery
and Intrigue they reserved more for
darker moods creating a lot of
underlying suspense these sound effects
are so good because they kind of manipul
ulate the viewer's emotions which is so
powerful because the more emotionally
invested the viewer is the more engaged
they are and these sound effects are
just the tip of the iceberg to achieve
this below the surface is a massive
potential for emotional investment your
music choice for example I like to find
songs that create a feeling of
anticipation which makes the viewer
constantly believe I'm about to say
something super important then during a
segment where I'm giving groundbreaking
advice I use a song that gives an
Innovative feeling which creates a ton
of excitement over what I'm saying this
is super straightforward to pull off
separate your video based on subject
changes and then decide the mood the
viewer should have for each subject by
the way you should spend a lot of time
finding the right music because it is
really important that it fits you can
find some good copyright free songs on
the YouTube audio library and there's
the occasional gem artist like let me
know which offers free songs but to be
honest subscribing to a licensed music
platform is the best choice if you're
going to take YouTube seriously I'm not
sponsored but I saved like 4 hours with
them last time and I found way better
songs I have an affiliate link for them
in the description okay this is going to
sound crazy but there's even more you
can do with your music choice to immerse
the viewer like what do you think
happens if you pause the music abruptly
the sudden change will jolt the viewer
getting their attention also the lack of
music brings attention to other parts of
the video so for special moments try
pausing the music to elev at that moment
now what if you instead let the music
slowly fade out once the viewer notices
that the music is going away they'll
understand that the segment they're
watching is coming to a close this
realization gives them anticipation of
something new coming okay let's get even
more advanced Beyond just making the
mood of the song match the tone of the
segment it's in upgrade your music by
sinking the hits and dips of the song to
the video for example in this segment I
introduced the problem here and began
teaching the solution here I line things
up so that at this exact moment the
music picks up doing that marks a clear
topic shift from problem to solution and
also makes the solution segment more
exciting and if you're wondering why I
have four music tracks playing at the
same time it's because I downloaded the
separate elements of the song that's
another feature of epidemic sound which
is super helpful all right I hope that
helped now there's a lot more to
retention so click here for a video on
that and then you're interested in that
call thing there's a link below